#大家好 今天我們來做點這池子
Hi everyone! We are here today to build some cells.
#你看 現在做得[SIC]池子都是這個繁殖池
Look! The cells that we are now building are all breeding cells.
#現在主要我們這間房都全部做得[SIC]是繁殖池
Now mainly, the cells we built in this room are all breeding cells.
#昨天我們做了一下午
We spent the whole afternoon yesterday,
#就做了那幾個
to build those cells over there.
#做了不多 做了應該20個吧
Not many. I think, perhaps around 20.
#這個比較難做
It's a bit tricky to build.
#又要做好看一點 又要做
We want the cells to look better, and,
#又要做得那個標準一點
and, you know, to be more consistent.
#所以做得特別慢
That's why we are building really slowly.
#不像我們以前一樣
It's not like before,
隨便做
when we did not care that much.
#現在我們來做幾個
Let's build several here.
#現在天氣還沒黑 (註︰用Weather確是有點怪，但他又確是說「天氣」)
The weather now is still not yet dark.
#天還未黑
I mean there's still daylight.
可以多做幾個池子
We can build some more cells.
#缺了一個角
A corner is missing.
#放到下面去
Put it at the bottom.
#這就看不到
Then it's no longer visible.
#先墊高一點
Raise it a bit.
#用磚頭壓一下就可以把它固定住
It can be stabilized by putting a brick on top of it.
#像做這個池子很快的
It doesn't take much time to build this kind of cells.
#先墊一下 把它墊平
This is for levelling off the cells.
#這邊上我們粘點玻璃膠去就好啦
Just put some silicone sealant onto the edges. Then it's done.
#好 這樣就
A cell,
#這樣就做好一個啦
a cell is then completed.
#再用這個瓷板壓一下
Then I press it with another ceramic tile.
#今天把兄弟也叫過來 他在外面鏟沙子啊
I've asked my buddy to come here today. He is shovelling the sand outside.
#我們去看一下
Let's take a look.
#我們把外面那個坪稍微打一下 (註︰完全不知道甚麼叫「打一下」)
We'll take care of the empty space outside.
#用水泥打 澆一下 (註︰不明用，隨便譯而已)
with cement, pouring some cement.
#不然的話放竹子 (註︰這兩句是前言對後語的)
Otherwise the bamboo...
#用那個平放竹子可以啊
The space can be used for laying bamboo.
#他在那邊鏟沙子
He's shovelling the sand over there.
#鏟那沙子鋪這邊
The sand will be put on this side.
#把這邊鋪好來 鋪好來放竹子
We'll pave this part, pave it to put the bamboo here.
#到時候竹子直接推到這里
Then the bamboo can be carried on a cart all the way here.
#全部缷這里 然後就可以切
Unload, cut them up,
#切碎來給那個竹鼠吃 (註︰他的「切碎」其實只是指砍成段)
and bring to the bamboo rats right away.
#你看 這邊我們也清洗了一下
Look! We've also washed the floor here,
#準備在這邊也要做 做池子
so that we can build, build the cells here as well.
#把它做滿
Full of cells.
#這個我們也打算不拆啦
I'll keep this one here.
#把竹鼠放到這裡面
I can put the bamboo rats here
#那個小竹鼠哇
the baby rats,
#放夠100個下去
a hundred of them,
#讓他們自由生長
to let them grow freely.
#想抓 想吃的時候就來這裡直接抓
Whenever I wanna catch, I mean, to eat, I can just catch one here.
#直接跳到這池子裡面 這麼大的池子
I can simply jump into the cell. It's such a large cell.
#到時我把這個門也堵掉它去
I'll block this door.
#把那些 那些東西清出來之後
After clearing all the stuffs inside,
#我就把這個門堵掉
I'll block this door.
#不要留那麼多門
There're too many doors.
#這裡面很涼快的哦 這裡面
It's very cool inside. It's cool,
#好涼爽
inside.
#一點都不熱
It's not hot at all.
#外面30(多)[SIC]度 這邊只有20多度的
It's more than 30 degrees outside. But it's not even 30 here.
#等一下我們準備把這裡清洗一下
I'm about to wash the floor here.
#清洗一下 過兩天我們又可以做池子
Wash the floor, then we can start building the cells here in a couple of days.
#在這邊全部做
Here will be full of cells.
#因為那個做那個竹鼠池啊
Cuz, you know, building the cells,
#要自己親自做 (註︰我把次序換了一點以更乎合英語的語法和習慣)
is not possible if not,
#親自做 或者叫
by myself, myself, or
#養 養過竹鼠的人做 才做得了
by someone who has, has the experience in raising bamboo rats.
#要是請得外面的工人做 做不了的
I can't hire other workers. They simply don't know how.
#自由[SIC]自己慢慢去做 (註︰我覺得應該只「只有自己慢慢去做」)
So I can only do it slowly by myself.
#這邊到時候我們砌磚
We'll pile up the bricks here.
#叫工人一起把它砌過去
I can hire some workers to pile up the bricks all the way here to there.
#我下河邊看一下
Let me go down to the riverside to have a look.
#那個好像有黑在那裡跳
It seems that the fish are jumping,
#跳來跳去的
jumping around.
#你看這裡 好多魚喲
Look! Here're a lot of fish.
#通通[SIC]出來
Get out!
#哇 全部在石頭上
Wa! They're all on the rocks.
#好多魚
A lot of fish!
#你看這個水潭
Have a look at this pond.
#這水潭很深的哦
The water here is very deep.
#下次我們用魚竿來釣
I'll see if I can catch some by a fishing rod next time.
#釣不到我就用抽水機來抽
If not, I'll bring my draining machine,
#放乾它 放乾這裡的水
to drain, drain away all the water,
#看我能不能把它抓住
and see if I can catch them then.
#好多魚喲
A lot of fish!
#這個
This is,
#石斑魚
"shi ban yu" (untranslatable grouper)
#沒看到鯽魚 鯽魚肯定在那深水裡面藏起來啦
I can't see any "ji yu" (untranslatable carps). They must be hiding under the deep water.
#下次來
I'll come again,
#我們有空的時候就拿魚鈎來勾它
with my fishing hook next time, when we're not that busy.
#我們到下面去看一下
Let's go down there to take a look.
#下面很我[SIC]這樣的水潭
There're a lot of ponds of this kind.
#先看好 然後再帶抽水機過來
Let's take a look first, and then come again with the draining machine,
#抽 (註︰這個字其實不譯會更通順，但視覺感覺則不太良好)
to drain.
#下面好幾個水潭都有魚喲
I saw fish in quite a number of ponds down there.
#下次我們帶抽水機過來
We'll come again with the draining machine.
#這樣方便一點 現在甚麼都沒帶 不方便
It'll be much easier then. Not now. We don't have any tools with us.